Twenty-five-and-a-quarter years ago I read
قبل خمس وعشرين عاماً وربع قرأت
a newspaper article which said
مقالاً في الصحيفة فيه
that one day syringes would be
أنه في أحد الأيام ستكون الحقن
one of the major causes of the spread of AIDS,
أحد الأسباب الرئيسية لإنتشار مرض الإيدز،
the transmission of AIDS.
لإنتقال مرض الإيدز.
I thought this was unacceptable. So I decided to do something about it.
ظننت أن هذا أمر غير مقبول. لذا قررت أن أفعل شيئاً حيال الأمر.
Sadly, it's come true. Malaria, as we all know,
بكل أسف، أنه أمر واقع. الملاريا، كما نعلم جميعاً،
kills approximately one million people a year.
تقتل تقريباً مليون شخص سنوياً.
The reuse of syringes now exceeds that
إعادة إستخدام الحقن الآن يزيد على ذلك
and kills 1.3 million people a year.
ويقتل 1.3 مليون شخص سنوياً.
This young girl and her friend
هذه الفتاة الصغيرة وصديقها
that I met in an orphanage in Delhi
الذين إلتقيتهم في دار أيتام في دلهي،
were HIV positive from a syringe.
مصابين بالإيدز عبر الحقنة.
And what was so sad about this particular story
وما كان محزناً للغاية في هذه القصة تحديداً
was that once their parents had found out --
كان أنه بمجرد أن علم ذويهم بالأمر،
and don't forget, their parents took them to the doctor --
ولا تنسوا، أن والديهم أخذوهم الى الطبيب،
the parents threw them out on the street.
قام والديهم برميهم في الشارع.
And hence they ended up in an orphanage.
ولذا فقد أنتهى بهم الحال في دار الإيتام.
And it comes from situations like this where
وأنها تأتي من مثل هذه الحالات حيث
you have either skilled or unskilled practitioners,
يكون لديك إمّا ممارسين مهرة أو غير مهرة،
blindly giving an injection to someone.
بصورة عمياء يقومون بحقن شخص ما.
And the injection is so valuable,
والحقن أمر قيّم للغاية،
that the people basically trust
حتى أن الناس يثقون في الأساس
the doctor, being second to God, which I've heard many times,
بالطبيب، كونه قريب من الخالق، ما سمعته في كثير من الأوقات،
to do the right thing. But in fact they're not.
ليفعل الشئ الصحيح. لكن في الواقع ليسوا كذلك.
And you can understand, obviously, the transmission problem
ويمكنكم أن نفهم، من الواضح، أن مشكلة الإنتقال
between people in high-virus areas.
بين الناس في المناطق المعرضة بشدة للفيروس.
This video we took undercover,
هذا الفيديو تم أخذه بصورة سرّية،
which shows you, over a half an hour period,
الذي يبيّن لكم على مدى فترة نصف ساعة،
a tray of medicines of 42 vials,
علبة دواء من 42 قارورة.
which are being delivered with only 2 syringes in a public hospital in India.
التي تم حقنها عبر حقنتين فقط في مستشفى عام في الهند.
And over the course of half an hour, not one syringe
وخلال فترة النصف ساعة، في التصوير
was filmed being unwrapped.
لم يتم تغيير أي حقنة منها.
They started with two and they ended with two.
لقد بدأوا بأثنين وأنتهوا بأثنين.
And you'll see, just now, a nurse coming back to the tray,
وكما ترون جميعاً، ممرضة تعود الى الدرج،
which is their sort of modular station,
والذي يشكل نوعا من وحدات المحطة،
and dropping the syringe she's just used
وترمي بالحقنة التي أستخدمتها للتو
back in the tray for it to be picked up and used again.
في الدرج حتى يتم إستخدامها مجدداً.
So you can imagine the scale of this problem.
إذاً يمكنكم تخيّل حجم هذه المشكلة.
And in fact in India alone, 62 percent
وفي الحقيقة في الهند وحدها، 62 في المائة
of all injections given
من كل الحقن التي تُحقن
are unsafe.
ليست آمنة.
These kids in Pakistan don't go to school.
هؤلاء الأطفال في باكستان لا يذهبون الى المدرسة.
They are lucky. They already have a job.
أنهم محظوظون. لديهم بالفعل عمل.
And that job is that they go around and pick up syringes
وذلك العمل هو البحث وإلتقاط الحقن
from the back of hospitals,
من خلف المستشفى،
wash them, and in the course of this,
غسلها، وفي هذه الأثناء،
obviously picking them up they injure themselves.
بالطبع خلال إلتقاطها يقومون بجرح أنفسهم.
And then they repackage them and sell them out on markets
ثم يقومون بإعادة تغليفها وبيعها في الأسواق
for literally more money
من أجل مزيد من المال ، حرفياً
than a sterile syringe in the first place, which is quite bizarre.
عن الحقن المعقمة، في المقام الأول. ما يبدو غريباً جداً.
In an interesting photo, their father, while we were talking to him,
وفي صورة مثيرة ، والدهم، بينما كنا نتحدث إليهم،
picked up a syringe and pricked his finger --
إلتقط حقنة ووزخر أصبعه--
I don't know whether you can see the drop of blood on the end --
لا أعرف سواء كان بإمكانكم رؤية قطرات الدم في النهاية --
and immediately whipped out a box of matches,
وفي الحال نزع عوداً من علبة الثقاب،
lit one, and burned the blood off the end of his finger,
يشعله، ويحرق الدم في نهاية أصبعه،
giving me full assurance
أعطاني تأكيد كامل
that that was the way that you stopped the transmission of HIV.
أن تلك هي الطريقة التي توقف بها إنتقال الإيدز.
In China, recycling is a major issue.
في الصين، إعادة التصنيع قضية رئيسية.
And they are collected en mass -- you can see the scale of it here --
ويتم جمعها بشكل جماعي-- يمكنكم رؤية الحجم هنا --
and sorted out, by hand, back into the right sizes,
وتسويتها، بالأيدي، رجوعاً الى الحجم الصحيح،
and then put back out on the street.
وبعد ذلك إرجاعها الى الطرقات.
So recycling and reuse
إذاً إعادة التصنيع وإعادة الإستخدام
are the major issues here.
هما قضيتان رئيسيتان هنا.
But there was one interesting anecdote that I found in Indonesia.
لكن كانت هناك طرفة مثيرة وجدتها في أندونسيا.
In all schools in Indonesia,
في كل المدارس في أندونسيا،
there is usually a toy seller in the playground.
يوجد عادة بائع لُعب في الملعب.
The toy seller, in this case,
بائع اللُعب ، في هذه الحالة،
had syringes, which they usually do,
لديه حقن، التي تكون في العادة،
next door to the diggers, which is obviously
قرب الحُفر، ومن الطبيعي
what you would expect.
أن يحدث ما تتوقعه.
And they use them, in the breaks, for water pistols.
ويقومون بإستخدامها، في فترات الراحة، كمسدسات ماء.
They squirt them at each other, which is lovely and innocent.
يقومون برش بعضهم البعض. الشئ الجميل والبرئ.
And they are having great fun.
ويقضون أوقاتاً رائعة للغاية.
But they also drink from them
لكنهم أيضاً يشربوا منها
while they're in their breaks, because it's hot.
أثناء تواجدهم في فترات الراحة، لأن الطقس حار.
And they squirt the water into their mouths.
ويقومون ببخ الماء على أفواههم.
And these are used with traces of blood visible.
وتستخدم هذه مع بقايا دماء واضحة للعيان.
So we need a better product. And we need better information.
لذا فنحن في حوجة لمنتج أفضل. نحتاج لمعلومات أفضل.
And I think, if I can just borrow this camera,
وأعتقد، إذا قدرت على إقتراض هذه الكاميرا،
I was going to show you my invention,
كنت سأقوم بعرض إبتكاري عليكم،
which I came up with.
الشئ الذي توصلت له.
So, it's a normal-looking syringe.
إذاً، أنها حقنة تبدو عادية.
You load it up in the normal way. This is made
تقوم بملئها بطريقة عادية. هذا مصنوع
on existing equipment in 14 factories that we license.
بناء على معدات موجودة في 14 مصنعاً قمنا بالترخيص لها.
You give the injection and then put it down.
تقوم بالحقن وبعد ذلك تقوم بوضعها.
If someone then tries to reuse it,
إذا حاول شخص آخر إعادة إستخدامها،
it locks and breaks afterwards.
فأنها تؤمنّ وتنكسر .
It's very, very simple. Thank you.
أنها بسيطة جداً جداً. شكراً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
And it costs the same as a normal syringe.
وتبلغ كلفتها نفس كلفة الحقنة العادية.
And in comparison, a Coca-Cola
وفي مقارنة، علبة كوكا كولا
is 10 times the price.
10 أضعاف سعر الحقنة.
And that will stop reusing a syringe 20 or 30 times.
وهذا سيوقف إعادة إستخدام الحقنة 20 أو 30 مرة.
And I have an information charity
ولديّ مؤسسة خيرية للمعلومات
which has done huge scale amount of work in India.
التي قامت بحجم ضخم من العمل في الهند.
And we're very proud of giving information to people,
ونحن فخورون جداً بتقديم المعلومات الى الناس
so that little kids like this don't do stupid things.
بحيث لا يفعل الأطفال الصغار مثل هذا أفعالاً غبية.
Thank you very much.
شكراً جزيلاً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)